[Music]
Reedman
reads The Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser
Reedman chapter
[Music]
14 It was much the same, this memory, though the hill seemed to be a different
one, steeper, and the snow was not falling as thickly as it had
before. It was colder, also, Jonas perceived. He could see, as he sat waiting
in the top of the hill, that the snow beneath the sled was not thick and soft
as it had been before, but hard, and coated with bluish ice. The sled moved forward, and Jonas
grinned with delight, looking forward to the breathtaking slide down through the invigorating
air. But the runners, this time, couldn't sliced through the frozen expanse that
they had on the other snow cushioned hill. They skittered sideways and the
sled gathered speed. Jonas pulled at the rope, trying to steer, but the steepness
and speed took control from his hands and he was no longer enjoying the
feeling of freedom but instead, terrified, was at the mercy of the wild
acceleration downward over the ice. Sideways, spinning, the sled hit a
bump in the hill and Jonas was jarred loose and thrown violently into the air.
He fell with his leg twisted under him I could hear the crack of bone. His face
scraped along jagged edges of ice and when he came, at last, to a
stop, he lay shocked and still, feeling nothing at first but
fear. Then, the first wave of pain. He gasped. It was as if a hatchet
lay lodged in his legs slicing through each nerve with a hot blade. In his agony
he perceived the word "fire" and felt flames licking at the torn bone and
flesh. He tried to move, and could not. The pain grew. He screamed. There was no answer.
Sobbing, he turned his head and vomited onto the frozen snow. Blood dripped from
his face into the vomit no he cried, and the sound disappeared into the empty
landscape, into the wind.
Then, suddenly, he was in the Annex room again Rising on the bed. His face was wet with
tears. Able to move now, he rocked his own body back and forth, breathing deeply to
release the remembered pain. He sat, and looked at his own leg, where it lay
straight on the bed, unbroken. The brutal slice of pain was
gone. But the leg ached horribly, still, and his face felt
raw. "May I have relief of pain please?" he begged he was always provided in his
everyday life for the bruises and wounds, for a mashed finger, a stomach ache, a
skin knee from a fall from a bike. There was always a do of anesthetic
ointment, or a pill; or in severe instances, an injection that brought
complete and instantaneous deliverance.
But The Giver said no, and looked away. Limping, Jonas walked home, pushing
his bicycle, that evening. The sunburn pain had been so small, in comparison, and
had not stayed with him. But this ache lingered. It was not unendurable, as the
pain on the hill had been. Jonas tried to be brave. He
remembered that the Chief Elder had said he was brave.
"Is something wrong, Jonas?" his father asked at the evening meal. "You're so
quiet tonight. Aren't you feeling well?
Would you like some medication?" But Jonas remembered the
rules. No medication for anything related to his training. And no discussion of his
training. At the time for sharing of feelings he simply said that he felt
tired, that his school lessons had been unusually demanding that
day. He went to his sleeping room room early, and from behind the closed door he
could hear his parents and sister laughing as they gave Gabriel his evening
bath. They have never known pain, he thought. The realization made him feel
desperately lonely, and he rubbed his throbbing leg. He eventually
slept. Again and again he dreamed of the anguish and the isolation on the forsaken
hill. The daily training continued, and now it always included pain. The agony of
the fractured leg began to seem no more than a mild discomfort as The Giver led
Jonas firmly, little by little, into the deep and terrible suffering of the
past. Each time, in his kindness, The Giver ended the afternoon with a color-filled
memory of pleasure: a brisk sail on a blue green lake; a meadow dotted with
yellow wild flowers or an orange sunset behind mountains.
It was not enough to assuage the pain that Jonas was beginning, now, to
know. Why? Jonas asked him after he had received a torturous memory in which he
had been neglected and unfed; the hunger had caused excruciating spasms in his
empty, distended stomach. He lay on the bed, aching. "Why do you and I have to hold these
memories?" "It gives us wisdom," The Giver replied. "Without wisdom I could not
fulfill my function of advising the Committee of Elders when they call upon
me what wisdom do you get from hunger?"
Jonas groaned. His stomach still hurt, though the memory had
ended. "Some years ago," The Giver told him, "before your birth, a lot of citizens
petitioned the Committee of Elders. They wanted to increase the rate of
births. They wanted each birth mother to be assigned four births instead of three,
so that the population would increase and there would be more Laborers
available." Jonas nodded, listening. "That Mak sense." "The idea was that certainly family
units could accommodate an additional child." Jonas nodded again. "Mine could," he
pointed out. "We have Gabriel this year, and it's fun, having a third
child a Committee of Elders sought my advice," The Giver said. "It made sense to
them, too, but it was a new idea, and they came to me for
wisdom." "And you used your memories?" The Giver said yes. "And the strongest memory that came
was hunger. It came from many generations back. Centuries back. The population had
gotten so big that hunger was everywhere.
Excruciating hunger and starvation. It was followed by warfare."
Warfare? It was a concept Jonas did not know. But hunger was familiar to him
now. Unconsciously he rubbed his own abdomen, recalling the pain of its unfulfilled
needs. "So you describe that to them?"
"They don't want to hear about pain. They just seek the advice. I simply advise
them against increasing the population." "But you said that that was
before my birth. They hardly ever come to you for advice. Only when they— —what was
it you said? When they have a problem they never faced before. When did it happen
last?" "Do you remember the day when the plane flew over the community?" "Yes. I was scared."
"So were they. They prepared to shoot it down. But they sought my advice. I told them to
wait." "But how did you know? How did you know the pilot was
lost?" "I didn't. I used my wisdom, from the memories. I knew that there had been
times in the past— —terrible times— —when people had destroyed others in haste, in
fear, and had brought about their own destruction."
Jonas realized something. "That means," he said slowly, "that you have memories of
destruction. And you have to give them to me, too, because I have to get the
wisdom." The Giver nodded. "But it will hurt Jonah said. It wasn't a
question. "It will hurt terribly," The Giver agreed why can't everyone have the
memories I I think it would seem a little easier if the memories were
shared. You and I wouldn't have to bear so much by ourselves, if everybody took a
part." The Giver side You're right," he said everyone would be burdened and
pained. They don't want that. And that's the real reason The Receiver is so vital
to them, and so honored. They selected me— —and you— —to lift that burden from themselves."
"When did they decide that?" Jonas asked angrily. "It wasn't fair. Let's change it!"
"How do you suggest we do that? I've never been able to think of a way, and I'm
supposed to be the one with all the wisdom." "But there are two of us now Jonah
said eagerly. Together we can think of something!" The Giver watched him with a rise
smile. "Why can't we just apply for a change of rules Jonah suggested.
The Giver laughed; then Jonas, too, chuckled reluctantly. "The decision was
made long before my time or yours," The Giver said, "and before the previous Receiver, and—" He
waited. "Back and back and back." Jonas repeated the familiar
phrase. Sometimes it had seemed humorous to him. Sometimes it had seemed meaningful and
important. Now it was ominous.
It meant, he knew, that nothing could be
[Music]
changed. The new child Gabriel, was growing, and successfully passed the
tests of maturity that the Nurturers gave each month; he could sit alone, now,
could reach for and grasp small play objects, and he had six
teeth. During the daytime hours, Father reported, he was cheerful and seemed of normal
intelligence. But he remained fretful at night, whimpering often, needing frequent
attention. "After all this extra time I've put in with them Father said one evening
after Gabriel had been bathed and was lying, for the moment, hugging his hippo
placidly in the small crib that had replaced the basket, "I hope they're not going to
decide to release him." "Maybe it would be for the best," Mother suggested. "I know you
don't mind getting up with him at night.
But the lack of sleep is awfully hard for me." "If they release Gabriel, can we
get another new child as a visitor?" asked Lily. She was kneeling beside the crib,
making funny faces at the little one, who was smiling back at her. Jonas's mother
rolled her eyes in dismay.
"No," Father said, smiling. He ruffled Lily's hair. "It's very rare, anyway, that a new
child's status is as uncertain as Gabriel's. It probably won't happen again, for a long time.
"Anyway," he SED they won't make the decision for a while. Right now we're all
preparing for a release we'll probably have to make very soon. There's a birth
mother who's expecting twin males next month." "Oh, dear," Mother said, shaking her
head. "If they're identical, I hope you're not the one assigned—" "I am. I'm next on
the list. I'll have to select the one to get nurtured, and the one to be released.
It's usually not hard, though. Usually usually it's just a matter of birth
weight We release the smaller of the two."
Jonas, listening, thought suddenly about the bridge and how, standing there, he had
wondered what lay Elsewhere. Was there someone there, waiting, who would received
the tiny released twin? Would it grow up Elsewhere, not knowing, ever, that in this
community lived a being who looked exactly the same? For a moment he felt a
tiny, fluttering hope that he knew was quite foolish. He hoped that it would be Lissa
waiting Lissa the old woman he had bathed. He remembered her sparkling eyes,
her soft voice, her low chuckle. Fiona had told him recently that
Thea had been released at a wonderful ceremony he knew that the Old were not
given children to raise Lissa's life Elsewhere would be quiet and serene as befit the
Old; she would not welcome the responsibility of nurturing a new child
who needed feeding and care, and would likely cry at night. "Mother? Father?" he said, the idea
coming to him unexpectedly, "why don't we put Gabriel's crib in my room tonight? I know how to
feed and comfort him, and it would let you and Father get some sleep." Father looked
doubtful. "You sleep so soundly, Jonas. What if his restlessness didn't wake
you?" It was Lily who answered that. "If no one goes to tend Gabriel," she pointed out,
"he gets very loud. He'd wake all of us, if Jonas slept through
it." Father laughed. "You're right ly Billy All right, Jonas, let's try it, just for
tonight. I'll take the night off we'll let Mother get some sleep,
[Music]
too." Gabriel slept soundly for the earliest part of the
night. Jonas, in his bed, lay awake for a while; from time to time he raised
himself on one elbow, looking over at the crib. The new child was on his stomach,
his arms relaxed beside his head, his eyes closed, and his breathing regular and
undisturbed. Finally Jonas slept too. Then, as the middle hours of the
night approached, the noise of gab's restlessness woke Jonas. The new child was turning under
his cover, flailing his arms, and beginning to whimper. Jonas rose
and went to him. Gently he patted Gabriel's back. Sometimes that was all it took to
lull him back to sleep. But the new child still squirmed fretfully under his
hand. Still patting rhythmically jonus began to remember the wonderful saale
that The Giver had given him not long
before: a bright, breezy day on a clear turquoise lake, and above him the white sail of the
boat billowing as he moved along in the brisk
wind. He was not aware of giving the memory; but suddenly he realized that it
was becoming dimmer, that it was sliding through his hand into the being of the new
child Gabriel became quiet. Startled, Jonas pulled back what
was left of the memory with a burst of will. He removed his hand from the little
back and stood quietly beside the crib. To himself, he called the memory of
the sail forward again. It was still there, but the sky was less blue, the
gentle motion of the boat slower, the water of the lake more murky and
clouded. He kept it for a while, soothing his own nervousness at what had occurred,
then let it go and returned to his bed.
Once more, toward dawn, the new child woke and cried out. Again Jonas went to
him. This time he quite deliberately placed his hand firmly on Gabriel's back,
and released the rest of the calming day on the lake. Again Gabriel
slept. But now Jonas lay awake, thinking. He no longer had any more than
a whisp of the memory, and he felt a small lack where it had been. He could
ask The Giver for another sale he knew. A saale perhaps on the ocean, next time, for
Jonas had a memory of ocean, now, and knew what it was; he knew that there were sail
bolts there, too and memory is yet to be acquired. He wondered, though, if he should
confess to The Giver that he had given a memory away. He was not yet qualified to
be a Giver himself; nor had Gabriel been selected to be a
Receiver. That he had this power for frightened him. He decided not to tell
[Music]